Guide to the Wadsworth Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Wadsworth family papers
1745-1914
1775-1862
MS 525
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
Chiefly correspondence of the Wadsworth, Silliman, and Trumbull families. Of note in the eighteenth century correspondence is the exchange between Joseph Trumbull and Jeremiah Wadsworth concerning the business of the Commissary General during the American Revolution. Major correspondents in the later period are Faith Trumbull Wadsworth, Benjamin and Harriet Trumbull Silliman and their children. There is a long series of ninety-one letters (1806-1846) to Eliza Winthrop Sebor from Faith Trumbull Wadsworth and also a diary kept by her between 1803 and 1846. Another by John Noyes Wadsworth from 1790 to 1815 is largely made up of his financial accounts from Durham, Conn. and Genesee, New York. This volume was continued (1815-1835) by John's son, Wedworth. Also in the papers are miscellaneous legal and financial papers, clippings and memorabilia.
Wadsworth family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Maria Trumbull Dana, 1943.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The major part of this collection is approximately 250 letters received and sent by members of the Wadsworth, Silliman, and Trumbull families between 1745 and 1862. Most of the eighteenth-century letters are from Joseph Trumbull to Jeremiah Wadsworth, concerning business of the Commissary General during the Revolution. The later correspondence consists mainly of letters by Daniel and Faith (Trumbull) Wadsworth to Benjamin and Harriet (Trumbull) Silliman and their children and to Miss Eliza W. Sebor of Middletown. This family correspondence deals mainly with such personal matters as illness, death, visits, and gossip. The letters are indivually catalogued.
Among other items in this collection is a small diary of Faith Trumbull Wadsworth (Mrs. Daniel), mainly religious musings and family nostalgia, 1803-1846. This diary is in two small books copied by Susan Forbes Silliman (Mrs. Benjamin II), a great-niece of Mrs. Wadsworth. The other volume is an account of John Noyes Wadsworth, 1758-1815, a cousin of Colonel Jeremiah Wadsworth, begun in 1790 and continued after 1815 by John's son Wedworth until 1835. There are also notes, clippings, memorabilia, and legal and financial papers.
The Wadsworth Family papers were given to Yale University Library by Maria Trumbull Dana. There are related items in the Silliman Family papers and the John Trumbull papers.
Biographical / Historical
For charts outlining the genealogical relations of the Wadsworth, Sillman, and Trumbull families, please consult the Genealogical Charts.
Families; Connecticut; Durham (Conn.: Town); Genesee (N.Y.); United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Equipment and supplies; Account books; Diaries; DuBlanc, James; Fitch, Jonathan, 1727-1793; Mitchell, Stephen Mix, 1743-1835; Sebor, Eliza Winthrop; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Silliman, Faith Wadsworth, 1812-1887; Silliman, Maria Trumbull, 1810-1880; Stoddard, Josiah, 1747-1779; Terry, Catherine Wadsworth, 1774-1841; Trumbull, Eunice Backus, 1749-1826; Trumbull, John, 1756-1843; Trumbull, Jonathan, 1740-1809; Trumbull, Joseph, 1737-1778; Trumbull, Leverett, 1788-1807; Wadsworth, Daniel, 1771-1848; Wadsworth, Faith Trumbull, 1769-1846; Wadsworth, Jeremiah, 1743-1804; Wadsworth family
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - 1745-1746 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1775 Nov-1777 Nov (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1778 Jan-1795 Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1796-1806 Apr (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1807 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1808 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1809 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1809 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1810 Jul-1811 Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1812 Mar-1813 Nov (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1814 Oct-1819 Jun (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1820 Aug-1821 Nov (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1823 Jun-1824 Nov (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1825 Apr-1826 Oct (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1827 Jan-Dec (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1828 Apr-Nov (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1829 Jan-Aug (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1830 Jan-Dec (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1831 Mar-1832 Nov (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1833 Jan-1834 Sep (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1836 Jan-1837 Apr (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1838 Jan-Dec (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1839 Jan-Dec (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1840 Jan-Dec (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1841 Apr-1842 Oct (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1843 Mar-1846 Sep (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1856-1862, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Arguments prepared for debates by James Wadsworth (1730-1817), 1745 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ledger belonging to John Noyes Wadsworth, 1790-1835 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Journal of Faith (Trumbull) Wadsworth, 1803-1846 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Poem; critical notes on a book or manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Deeds of sale, 1826, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Clippings, 1855, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Account of funeral expenses for Henry C. Trumbull, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Tax receipts, 1830-1849 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Silk ribbon with printed obituary of Leverett Hubbard Trumbull, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 36)